welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
so check-ins feeling a tad annoyed but
in a very playful way and I'm well just
looking at Angie right now I kind of
just want to like play tag with him and
run away and be silly
[Music]
so welcome to the stoah I'm the steward
of the stoic peter lindbergh and the
stoah is a place for us to cohere and
dialogue about what matters most that
the knife's edge this moment and I
promise I'm not going to get bored by
saying that maybe maybe I will I don't
know we'll find out so today we have my
mentor my brother my friend Andrew
Taggert and he's going to talk about the
gift economy which is basically this
whole kind of project is is resting on
as the gift economy and I think yeah I
think I'll just stop there and how this
is gonna work is andrew has been share
his thoughts I'll warm up warm him up
with some questions and if you have any
questions write in the chat box and then
I'll give you I think most of you know
the drill at this point so that being
said I will allow Andrew to unmute
himself and hand it over to him
I think I'm muted you yeah I'm good now
[Laughter]
hi everyone it's nice nice to be here
some new faces and certainly some bold
ones you know looking very sweet today
those I can see all right I've been
living in a gift economy since the end
of 2011 and the Peter was joking recent
with me when he was saying that the gift
economy that was that was game be years
before game he was even talked about so
you can make about what you will
I was initially going to say quite a lot
today about the gift economy but I have
too much to say about it and therefore
the Zen thing to do and I'm quite Zen
inspired it is to say very little about
it and instead to allow for the
questions to arise and then I think it
will become more coherent what this
model is
so the the first thing I think to do is
just as best you can
let go of everything you've read from Z
friends if French anthropologists but as
a gift economy a long long time ago so
let's just drop drop what you've read
there and drop what you've read
elsewhere or what you've heard about
gift economies Peter says he's the
Oviatt I go back to Z French okay I do
many exits this is just one so we need
we need to come to what Hakka want the
Zen master calls don't know mine first
because you've no doubt heard a number
of things about gift economies so begin
with the Socratic understanding I do not
know what I thought I did
you
okay so just sink into that sense of
expansive openness and wide open
listening
the next thing I want to say is that
it's not as if the gift economy
and an exchange model are like chocolate
and vanilla
they're not on the same ontological
plane
it's rather as if the market system is
the waking state and the gift economy is
the dream state
fundamentally different
they actually inhabit absolutely
different worlds worlds of beam so allow
that to sink in a little bit they were
not talking about things that are
comparable we're talking about
fundamentally different systems because
the mind is going to want to say it's
rather like what I know it's rather like
what I'm used to and so I'm just
inviting us to sink into this space of
unfamiliarity
which will also paradoxically be quite
familiar to us than the final analysis
next I'd like to start out by tying a
myths a myth or a mythos which is what
Plato used to do and the Methos is meant
to introduce us to this fundamentally
different way of understanding and if
you want and called a fairy tale that's
fine too so imagine a land far far away
or very very distant it's other science
fiction or it's a fairy tale or a
parable or some such and in this land
far far away imagine that there's a
people and there are two important
features in this place one there's a
group of artists about whom more in a
moment and the other thing we'll notice
is that there's a house of worship set
aside the house of worship for now
now in
far far away place as people these
people indeed others are so amazed by
these artists not by what they make but
by how they live the end mass in unison
they say to themselves we love them so
we admire them so that we wish to
support them
we will do whatever is necessary and not
beyond what is necessary to support the
lives of artists and the artists are
just filled with such a level of joy and
gratitude that they are that they begin
and continue to live these very
beautiful lives
the lives committed to let's even call
it sacred
Archer contemplative art they no feel
well if they don't have to create
anything
in any way that is exchangeable for what
they've received they know that in their
hearts and their very beings
what's really quite astonishing is that
out of a kind of fecundity of spirit
artworks begin to so to speak create
themselves and they go to the people at
one point and say we have come up with
these beautiful artworks and we think
that this piece might be wonderful in
the public square or that piece that
sculpture might be wonderful
on this corner or this could be a great
mural and the people wholeheartedly
accept
that gift
what's important to notice here is that
or lies too much it's just that there is
no tit for tat the artwork comes from a
place of fecundity and it is not coming
out of a place of beholden to nests or
indebtedness
so I once had a patron and all I did it
was provide money to me once every three
months me wish nothing in return
right so we're eating it's allegory of
the fundamentally probably totally
idealistic patronage of the Arts now
come back to the church just to see one
other example a matter the house of
worship so imagine people come into this
sacred place and every time they come in
there they feel that there is something
lifting them up say to a higher plane of
reality whatever they always feel better
every time they come in they feel better
it's like the stole all right and just
like this dog come in here you always
saw better and and you understand
something and things seem clear to you
not uncommonly people will say to
themselves I would like to support this
house in worship not because of what I
have received on any given occasion but
in order that the place itself shall
poor door that as it shall continue to
exist for the sake of others
so out of the gift out of a number of
gifts this house of worship continues to
exist so I hope that I hope those myths
is kind of conjoin myths give you
something of the taste of of the nature
of a gift economy to keep it brief I'm
just going to say a few words about my
own I was thinking about Homo economicus
before the conversation about the
critique of this LeMat but I think it'd
be good just to keep it rather
nuts-and-bolts impractical okay so if we
ask ourselves the question what are the
basic ways in which homo sapiens have
survived throughout the course of human
history
I would submit that there have only ever
been three three basic models and they
can be conjoined in sundry ways but
let's keep them separate for now one
would be that they've lived off the land
we have lived off the land be it through
hunting and gathering or be it through
the invention of agriculture that's the
first one Wendell Berry might come to
mind here for those who are familiar
with his writings he's advocating for a
return to and living off of the land you
can also think of back the land
movements from the 1919 60s and
following the second way refers to
market transactions for market exchanges
for those who know me just bear in mind
that I'm not critical of any market
whatsoever I'm critical of what Karl
Polanyi called the market system the
market system transforms human life in
such a way that markets begin to be
conjoined to markets and markets and
markets land becomes market and real
estate real estate becomes a market for
complex financial trading and so forth
so the ground upon which we stand no
longer it seems to be a home in the same
way in any case the second way is
through various forms of exchange you're
taking 4/10 we should be clear about
that that ranges from any exchange of
money for a service or money for a
product to exchanging one yoga session
for one coaching session that's still in
exchange by my lights the third way that
human beings have tended survive is
through what I generously call a gift or
forms of gift that's why I use the
example of the patron of the arts or I
used obviously a very idealized example
of house of worship to try to give you a
first feel for what it's like for there
to be communities they're oriented
around genuine forms of giving and
receiving in a non tit-for-tat manner so
lastly before return to questions and
answers I'm going to just
oh very briefly give you a sense of how
I've thought through this over the years
what won't be clear from what I'm about
to say is that a gift economy has a few
vital elements one is timing it's not
going to become clear because my
thoughts are compressed into a space of
just a couple minutes but you have to
imagine that the economic transaction is
instantaneous and frictionless but gift
giving and receiving is slow and it
follows an entirely different
temporalities when you get what you give
when you give the gift and how you give
the gift and with what graceful timing
all come to matter and we know this from
our own lives if your mother if your
mother happens to give you a birthday
gift
two weeks after birthday you know that
something has gone awry there and if
someone gives you a gift
three days before your birthday
something has also gone awry so you can
begin to see that a little bit when it
comes to the gift economy have come up
with a particular way of inquiring which
I call a direct inquiry into the gift
economy it's quite complicated but
here's a very simple version so I
philosophize the people philosophizing
is its own sort of thing a bit like the
artists example I gave or the house of
worship example I gave providing gifts
to support the life I lead is an
entirely different sort of thing I'm
talking about that different sort of
thing and what follows there are three
questions I tend to ask people at a
particular moment in our relationship
the first question is called the
question of proper generosity the second
question is called that of onus or
burden and the third question has called
the question of wholeheartedness and I
think this is actually a frilly it's a
meditation but it's also analytical
process and I think if you actually went
through your thinking and you'd find
this is actually what our thinking does
when it's going well when it is the case
we get a gift so the first question I
ask people is how much during a certain
period in question that you can specify
are you able to give to me some material
needs
you
straw dinelli dense question I'm just
gonna leave it there and for now we
could unpack it later if we need to so
let's say this up someone comes up with
X like I can give X turn to question two
I ask if you were to give X during a
certain period in question
you can specify why we're doing so make
it difficult if not impossible for you
to care for yourself as well as those
depend upon you
dependents community members older
parents whatever
if the answer is yes it would make it
difficult we would return to question
one I would ask the question again the
person would come up with a number
that's less than the original answer
less than X if the person says no that
I'll usually go through a meditation
then involves allowing that person to
see that there's a range so I so if the
answer was ax I said she said no it
wouldn't make it difficult if not
impossible we would go up to a point
where there would be pain it's a
meditation that would be the pain of
over generosity I feel as if I'm giving
too much and therefore as if I am
sacrificing myself so in my view proper
generosity is not an act of sacrifice
then we would go down and we'd find that
there's a point at which there is a
different kind of pain the pain of under
generosity or what Aristotle called
miser leanness
and that's a different kind of pain
that's marked out now there's a range
we might go back to the first question I
would ask it again
can come up with the same answer give
initially which was X or a number that's
in that range I asked the second
question again
be difficult if not impossible the
person let's say says no then we come to
understand which of those different
answers is the right one which one sits
well on you which one feels right it's
an intuitive response but everyone has
it actually everyone I'm spoken with so
let's say that person says X X feels
rank then I ask the question are you
willing to say then that X is neither
too much to give and light of your
current material circumstances nor too
little to give in light of your current
material circumstances but more or less
just enough or the right amount
if the person says no it's like chutes
and ladders we'll go back to the first
question and I'll ask it again I'll put
them back down the person says yes it
feels like the right amount just enough
just just enough and we come to the last
question the questionable hardness this
is a hard line question for those
interested in meditation you sink down
into the heart mind I ask the question
if you were to give X during this period
in question could you do so
wholeheartedly that is without
reservation without hesitation without
contraction now burdened could you do so
freely seamlessly easily wholeheartedly
it just comes off the hand just like
water the person can say yes then I
reply by saying yes I can accept the
gift wholeheartedly
so there's a
about where that fits in and it sounds
as if I just shot it out of a cannon at
you but I want to turn to questions and
I think this will become clearer as we
go along great so if you have a question
for Andrew just write in the chat box
I'll warm him up with a few so was
coming up mine is the psychological
hurdles both with receiving a gift and
giving a gift and for my experience it's
been a sort of a spiritual practice both
both of those and I recall I don't know
when it was it that you and I first
started 1982 vampires 2013 2013 Wow
and I remember when I first we first was
a Skype actually we first Skyped each
other in and he started running me
through those questions I'm like hey
this guy's weird he's weird
I got converted but I imagine you
experience that you know that tension
like people like like what this is weird
this is like you know unusual so how do
you kind of on board people to that
process and or what opportunity
opportunity friend yeah part of the
prototyping process it's so when I said
the temporality matters it really does
so consider that someone has contacted
me really timing timing really matter so
someone contacted me a month ago and
then maybe a couple weeks later we go
through a process of writing to one
another to see whether or not were
potentially a good companions as it were
and we might have our first call a call
just an introductory call we're just
jamming I just want to get a feel for
this person I hope this person wants to
get a feel for me and there might be
some more questions after the first call
it's got an extensive sense our meeting
and then there's a second call in which
I go through more logistics all I say
there is are you open so if you've
this far are you open to being weird and
the person says yes I'm open to being
weird like okay well I'll tell you more
about the gift economy later on but
let's just set it aside for now and
we'll hear more about it and then I'll
send some person some things to read
before our first philosophical
conversation and one of those will be
the gift economy inquiry and I'll say
you can read this think about a little
bit and then set it aside because you
don't want the shock value as I probably
was presented to you and then there's
the first philosophic conversation let's
say and there might be two actually but
notice how much time has elapsed is the
first written inquiry it's now been at
least a month or so and then the first
conversation might be a month or two
months so the philosophical conversation
might be a few months hence and then the
first gift economy continent we finally
get into it then I go through a very
strategic way of walking people through
it where there's a story at the
beginning and then there's a kind of an
exercise and then there's taking through
the process of what I've described in
about two minutes four people there and
then there's a series of questions and
answers
all of these things are meant to try to
kind of sink someone into that space
where it's very open very supple and the
person's already received a number of
gifts and obviously it knows at this
point that I'm not out I'm not out to -
- it's not some kind of trick so the
psychological defenses start to be
loosened through the lengthy process
that we've undertaken and then in the
conversation itself through that inquire
itself then there are some that will
arise and they will be the sorts of
things we can inquire into and other
philosophical conversations so no I see
you have some kind of hang-ups around
money or a fear of scarcity okay well
we'll set that aside and we'll come back
to it so the the the the the lesson that
I've learned here is a kind of unfolding
of patience and wisdom
very difficult if it were just like that
so that you got my transactions or or
custom tour or on spot very good you go
to a gym and okay you have two weeks
free but you ready to sign up now yeah
so it's not weird we're not doing tit
for tat I'm I'm just philosophizing I'm
just doing what it is that I do at some
point this person can turn if she feels
desire to to support the life I'm
leading mm-hmm I have a strong desire to
hear you snap one more time translation
okay thank you so I have two more
questions and uh the other one so that's
kind of the thing I want to turn to the
giving of a gift right now and I was
actually talking to
Raven about this and I noticed like some
viewing the stoah as a gift and
everything I'm doing out of this I view
as a gift to the world right now and and
Colin who you're gonna be talking to he
sort of started his own digital dance
studio it was inspired to a conversation
that we had and then it's kind of the
same model of the stoah where he's sort
of the steward and he's having more of
embodied practices and he's eating that
as a gift as well and I was telling
Raven it's like like there wasn't like a
fear of losing Colin because Colin was a
existential dance party every every
Thursday and there's a fear of losing
him as a facilitator is a fear of losing
Raven as a facilitator because they're
both super talented you're cool they
like this nice aesthetics and like I
want you to be part of stola you know
it's like it makes the gift even even
more cool and awesome
and so it's almost like I want to
engineer control the gift you know like
I want to control the outcome of a gift
but then it's not about that like I I
know when to lovely it's not about that
so it's just sort of that teasing
process and just letting that go hence
why I mentioned it feels like a
spiritual practice just getting this so
I wonder if you can speak on that and
maybe your experience with it yeah I
remember when I was first starting to
philosophize and I had all these cool
people wanting to philosophize me and so
I have you
including wow this is amazing this is so
this is so different from academia but
and what I was used to and the things
that were happening in the conversations
were so wild and interesting and you
know altered states of consciousness and
such they find this is really quite
something what's happening and so I
started to get attached to people and so
that that happens but you know the
simple lesson is that if you go through
a gift economy enough and if you go
through having a number of people
it's obviously Buddhist impermanence is
a Nietzsche you start to realize as you
have store as you've a philosophy
practice long enough that people will
come and go if they're an accord and it
becomes easier just to become less
attached because you think wow Colin's
lovely but I suspect that other people
are going to be interesting and
wonderful in different ways as well and
this is going to be this is going to be
a little like a tea shop in which people
come in they stay for a little while
some will stay but longer so I won't
take it as a so long and they'll hang
out there and some will just go once and
it's it's strange that mean we talk
about this in Buddhism Aiko and
Nietzsche
obviously you permanence things come and
go but when you start to actually taste
impermanence then you relax and you
realize that there's nothing to hold on
to
I won't you know I won't perish even if
the stove perishes
I won't perish even it's the philosophy
practice perishes and it's going to
continue to unwind as long as it unwinds
and to be whatever it is it's quite
amazing man I'm trying to put this into
words but it's the sentiment the feeling
the felt sense as you call it becomes
very clear mm-hmm yeah I just have a was
like grateful that I know you so the the
the last question is and I told you this
already so when I like so I've been
receiving gifts in the form of how and
you know kind of like people are
programming things and stuff like that
and people are also gifting money and
via PayPal and I mentioned this before
some somewhere but so I took a break
last week from all these like day one
insights and like I just like take it
together take a break and just watch a
movie and so we watched a Camille and I
we watched the Guy Ritchie movie and I
paid with that with the PayPal money and
it's just like a freaking like a ray of
light just felt like Shh
just like you know shining on me this is
so pure like I never felt that at all
buying anything but I bought it with
that gift money and then it just felt so
right oh my gosh it's so sad she was
onto something with this let's get the
kind of thing saying you said you had a
similar experience I'm wondering like
what's going on there I just remember
well I think people here know what it's
like to receive a gift
and it might be in the form of money and
it came out of the blue and someone said
I was thinking of you or I thought you
could use this or here it feels amazing
it's extraordinary it might even be not
that much money
now contrast that with category to the
market situation we're talking about if
only briefly before you did some kind of
gig a freelance gig an accounting owes
you money and you're following up with
accounting thrice you've and you've to
ring to bring that freaking check out of
them and you finally get it what do you
feel relief
at best that's the phenomenology I feel
relieved
you feel nothing if the Paycheck comes
over two weeks or you feel relieved
the tastes are totally different I
remember so this is the experience I was
telling you about that I was living in
Apple ash at the time we didn't have
much back in 2003 2013 my wife and I and
I received money and I sent this person
a picture of logs we were doing that I
said here's what hey hey here's what I
got with it was a wood-burning stove we
were using to keep warm I was amazing
feeling money transformed actually into
logs utilized to keep us warm
all right so questions I think you might
know this guy Daniel would you like to
go off mute and yes my question is there
seems to be an interesting mutually
affirming relationship between the skill
or the disposition of giving gifts and
that of receiving them do any thoughts
on this and more specifically what does
it take to be more receptive to the
gifts of others yeah Oh both of them
require it's a beautiful question it's
good to see you man how are you doing if
it's such a beautiful question you over
time the you know we'd say this in
Aristotelian way but the more you're
actually involved in giving and
receiving the more there's a kind of
openness an impersonal openness as if
fringe teacher you know if Francis Ducey
would say you have to be very impersonal
it's a new personality you know I mean
to say that there's a that is to say you
start to feel as if it's not really
about this particular set of this
particular ego itself you start to feel
as if there's an open welcoming all
right right so you're sitting there you
have no idea whether someone's going to
give a gift and it's oh how much it
arrives and it's fine see and it's it's
it's a lot we might say or it's very
little and purposefully not using
numbers during a conversation today it's
a little that's a lot I actually just
had a philosophical conversation with a
woman today who go into the Cova 19
pandemic and having not having work that
she had booked needed to just talk to me
about the gift economy again and she
offered
less so there's the first thing is you
come to this kind of open receptive
space I think you're calling it when the
emails we were just chatting before
there's a spaciousness
that becomes your stance your basic
stance is spaciousness the other thing
though is that there has to think there
has to be something of an imagination
with regard to what it would be like for
this person do this
I knew this person was fearful of giving
less I knew that it required courage on
her part to be able to speak up and that
I knew that there was I knew enough
about her to realize that this was
really quite an act too brave in her
part to actually bring it up in the
first place rather than to skirt around
it so I was so I was just very moved by
the fact that she was willing to come
forward in this way and that was already
something that was sinking sinking into
me when it came to receiving I forget
I'm getting old and I forget your other
question I'm sorry that was about the
receptivity with respect to you
basically if if there is a relationship
between giving and receiving and whether
that's the receiving side of it is
something that we ought to get more
attention to because I don't think
people talk about that how there's like
a skill and actually receiving the gift
there's a skill on both the the
receiving okay so I'll just put it a
little more succinctly the the the the
skill involved in a giving is Kairos
you're kind of or dancing you panic get
it right when it comes to putting a gift
at the right time that's the beauty of
it I was thinking of you and I wanted to
offer it to you today and I knew you
would be here or you might be in this
way you know you might say giving let's
just be very poetic about ever being a
French thing it's an act of love you did
you get that that's it's marvelous so
that's what it's like
that's what's like I'm kidding in the
receiving end being on the receiving end
is a little bit like being someone who's
generally open to being surprised so
that's this position you're not shocked
you're not disappointed you you you
didn't have three expectations all of
which have been flout adhere hey wow
there's something rather than nothing
it's like the magician's trick in which
the bouquet you know comes out of
nowhere how about that so you you get
used you're gonna get used to the game
of peekaboo it's all interesting it's
all really quite wonderful does that
mean something
can you kind of and I'm trying to give
some childish again examples a Charlie
examples you really start to to learn
what it was like to live in a world
before Homo economicus before economic
man became hegemonic to put it more
academic language you remember that
actually you're capable Homo sapiens are
capable of giving and receiving and
being surprised by the sorts of things
we didn't seem coming and that surprises
just a delightful Alex Honnold did a
free solo climb of a dawn wall at the
top of he said they asked him how was it
missus you know you could have
carelessly felt fallen to his death he
said mister lifelong Jen you have a
question I actually do give and receive
gifts quite a lot as an artist it sir
seems to go with being an artist but
often there in the system there is
transactional people a lot in that
system who kind of feeding in because I
think but certainly in this world the
way we are now we can't seem to manage
without them so do you see this gifting
system something that can come work
globally oh I don't know the answer to
that question you're asking about scale
fair enough
so let me give you a I think a humble
answer first of all I take the Buddhist
term discernment you begin to discern
the kind of people with whom you may
wish to enter into this alternative
relationship there's a lot of
discernment there I think about how much
miss education how many vices we've
accrued going to scarcity
greed and so forth so you begin to
realize that some people are kind of
groovy and they're tuned in a different
way so you might invite them into an
alternative and you're learning together
with them to me that's the first version
of course you start something with
community people who have been
[Music]
properly discerned to be there and you
begin to see how the gifts circulate
there that's the first remark I wouldn't
begin and her current system plunk it in
the middle because you're going to find
that there are all kinds of tragedy the
comments they're going to be very
exceptions you're going to have bad
actors and so forth so you're setting
your cell phone in so what I didn't say
is that when I talked with those three
models very briefly living off the land
perspicuous use of markets and gifts
there's what when daniel would call here
skill when it comes to knowing when you
do one when you do the other when you do
the third if I'm going to a large
organization giving a talk I'm not going
to say okay now let's talk about the
gift economy no no I have unfortunately
have to enter into a different kind of
relationship which is like I call a ship
of fairness and it's what the market
will will bear yield here so I'm going
to charge what a speaker at this
particular level is going to charge
that's a skill I'm not going to enter
into an esoteric quasi-mystical
relationship with them because that's
not the sort of thing that they're tuned
into here I think that's one of the
things I noticed as well some artists
they're a little dogmatic okay I forgot
your gift it's just gonna be just gifts
well we're living in a kind of carry
between game a and game B so being
skillful requires learning the different
models and being sufficiently skillful
at them so that's the kind of first and
second remark the last one is a little
bit sophisticated philosophically and I
won't go too much into it but I don't
think there's anything called mean for
work and I'll just plant that seed today
for anyone who wants just to be a little
bit provoked so just a little
provocation what I do think is that an
artist has a kind of practice of sorts
is that my wife's an artist the art the
artist artists kind of revealed that's a
gift Lois I would talk about it in that
manner if you've ever read his book the
gift so the first step is that art
itself is a gift that's the ontology the
second step is
if you have to enter into selling your
art then there's a transmogrification of
the art object into a commodity and
that's for letting go takes place so it
was a gift
now it's transmogrified into something
that can be bought sold etc etc so
there's you know if we can get our
understanding clearer than in buddhist
terms a lot of the Duker and unnecessary
suffering that we ordinary experience
will start to subside
that's the these these exercises and
thought I just provided are meant to
allow us to sit more comfortably with
herself and be more at peace with
ourselves so an answer to your answer a
basic question I'm not persuaded that
you would begin by scaling up gift
economies I you would begin by these
experimentations experiments with it
such as the stoah see what happens with
them see if they can be replicated
elsewhere and move in a quasi viral
fashion rather than in a Silicon Valley
scaling up fashion yeah there resonates
Tyson you had a question hey Angie yes
good to see you it's good to see you in
this um the spark that I sense in your
expression and it's not gonna bug me and
I
yeah like lots of questions coming up
and let's see I'm curious in what in
what situation would you choose not to
work with someone that was inquiring
about a gift and and then also in what
cases if ever have you approached
someone and been like I have a gift
you also do that or are you primarily
having people inquire with you yeah I
think I'm curious about like B there's
this idea that people don't value what
they pay for and like or that money is
kind of someone paying for something
that's like the filter that would filter
out people that it wasn't important to
UM if they didn't pay for it so it's you
know let me come to that
I want to I want to come back to other
questions you have but I want to that
last part so there's a little
intervention people don't value what
they pay for that's in the second
category of market exchanges and that's
what we're accustomed to hearing the
really hard thing to see is I'll just
provide you with a little picture let's
imagine that art or philosophy or
whatever it is whatever you want to call
I'm gonna call it philosophy because I'm
so I'm accustomed to
that's this is it's my own art form so
let's imagine that philosophy is it's
one stream you philosophy philosophize
with someone else and say it has its own
rate it flows along at its own Taoist ik
and its own dialing stick away it is
entirely unto itself that's that is what
I'm here for
I opened myself to the other Emery
philosophize now let's imagine we went
all the way across the country there's
another stream but I early different
profile and characteristics and the
label will be gift economy has its own
flow it has its own way of lending
effectively that's supporting the body
my body and my wife's body notice the
way I told a story there are two
different streams with their own
properties their own manners of
proceeding
so a gift economy is such that it can't
actually Brook the possibility that you
you you you value what you pay for that
requires the equivalence relationship so
what I'm denying and a gift economy is
that there could ever be an equivalence
and this makes good intuitive sense when
you hear Socrates say that he would
never accept money exchange for
transaction is this office - he's
pointing to the sacred quality of
philosophy that's beyond price or if you
point if you if you go to manual Conti
says that there's certain things that
are beyond fancy price or a market price
I think it's maybe actually translated
fancy price I'm not mistaken that he's
pointing at something that we believe in
that there are certain things that
certainly don't fall into this paradigm
but we have bodies right there bodies
that perish they need to somehow be be
supported by food and other basic needs
so what is the hack here so to speak
that allows us to be consistent with
ourselves while also being able to
support ourselves
that's this two-streams metaphor and I
know that took a little while to to
explain but it's really important to be
clear about that
because each every time when you come to
even alternative communities and they're
grooving they say man just give whatever
give whatever you feel like you know
usually they're still involved in
transactions they're saying I felt good
about it so even you go to a Laplace
nough ten-day retreat it says it says
about Donna give based on what you've
benefited from here are you kidding me
that's just egoic it's another tit for
tat so what they really should say is
give out of the spirit of wanting other
people to benefit from this or something
like that so now when I come to your
questions after I've disentangle thank
you yeah my thing the the core of my
curiosity is how you personally choose
or maybe create filters or how yeah and
in what cases you would choose not to
work with someone yeah
I wouldn't call work but we'll get onto
that some other time
Jose contemplate or philosophize all
right so yeah so there at least a number
of different ways of sorting that out
but here are ways that I've mattered to
me one I look for someone who's very
reliable or conscientious if I'm going
to sit down and philosophize with
someone I want to be the case that
person is there I don't have to worry
about that or if I write a note to that
person I want that person to be able to
know that he or she can write a note
back it should be like a dance
there's there's it's it's so clear it's
so very clear so rescheduling isn't just
an admin problem it suggests that
there's been a certain failure in the
relationship something is awry here all
right so that's what I mean by
conscientiousness or reliability or
whatever you want to call that the
second the second characteristic is
courage because philosophy is tends to
take us to some dark places so the
person requires or needs to exhibit
intellectual and moral courage
and I could say more about that and I'm
moving quickly here that third one is
open-mindedness and open-heartedness I
think we know what that's like at the
stoah that is there's something that
it's like to be close-minded and shut
off
I wouldn't possible I would resist this
I know what I know it is so there's
nails like to be open-minded and
open-hearted someone really has to be
like that to philosophize and the last
one is there are many more but the last
one that's important here would be
inquisitiveness the person has to be
disposed to asking a question so those
are that's kind of the first screen
process is this true of this person and
then if we got into the gift economy and
the person said I'd like to offer you an
American penny they're all those sorts
of different cases we could look at I
like to offer you an American penny and
this person let's say happens to be a
CEO at a fortune 50 company
hypothetically speaking so it seems you
know patently unreasonable that a penny
is just enough for this person it's
being quite a bit more I would realize I
probably had that conversation right
there and then with that person but I
wouldn't have any more because what I'm
what I'm trying to cultivate as a
certain kind of relationship in which
there is the possibility of going along
together and someone who is obviously
been educated in such a ways to be so
grossly ungenerous and not to care about
generosity is probably not someone I
want to be around so when I philosophize
it's it's of the form I like it to be
around this person neither he or she's a
very lovely person wouldn't be lovely to
philosophize together
so I I take that process to be I take
that process very seriously
I don't just philosophize with anyone I
want to make sure that we're actually
jamming together
and there are different ways in which it
becomes clear that we're not if that's
true and if it can't be kind of the
resistance can't end but then it makes a
lot of sense just to say I think this is
this is not this is not that cool so
this this might be the last question
rheya you ask your question to Andrew
sure thanks hi Andrew my question so I
imagine that building this type of
economy has come with a lot of trial and
error and I was wondering what you view
as like the greatest strength or victory
of the gift economy and what has been
the biggest challenge in really
establishing like a cohesive foundation
of this type of exchange economy
community that's not an exchange but I'm
not trying to get hit too clear I just
want to be sure that's clear yeah
there's there's an exchange can only
occur when there's an equivalence
between like things so back to your
lovely questions the I think what's
there been this looks like two basic
successes the first is that someone as
an Orthodox is I have been able to
actually
the case with lots of people with whom I
philosophized over the last 10 years
that people are basically generous if
they're in the right conditions and
they're given the opportunity and
they're opened up so the claim that
human beings are fundamentally
self-interested self calculating utility
maximizing creatures I think isn't
grounded its historically contingent
economic phenomenon that's it that's a
huge success I think when you actually
I've just noticed that when people
actually open up they want to be
properly generous not self sacrificially
so properly so that's an astounding
rejection of classical classical
neoliberal economics that's that's a
success the other the other one's very
more meat potatoes if you will and say
my father is a frost and I grew up in a
prize from household dammit it's just
the case that I've been able to support
myself and my wife over the last nearly
a decade and we've we owned a house
which is not very American we own a
house here in a middle middle middle
class city but it gives a lie to the
idea that this is just an artist who
starving and he's just virtually
signaling it's a proof in the pudding
concept that's the only reason I
mentioned it okay so the greatest the
greatest well they've been a lot of
failures but I'll just give you some
funny examples okay it's early on I
didn't understand what I was doing and
unfortunately as I was pivoting from
exchanges or fees to gifts I I was
clueless and I entered into that
cluelessness with people with her most
classify him so the the the the my basic
axiom is if you're going to do something
pretty groovy then you need to lay a
very clear beautiful
non non new-agey bridge from where you
are to where you're going all right
you're going to take people along with
you you need to be very clear very
intelligible and I wasn't and that
was that was very unfortunate so I would
get some very interesting gifts while I
was living in New York City I got a pair
of tarped and I got a man with like a
bull penis penny container made of
seriously Peter I did and I've got some
artworks
a lot of artworks I'm living you know
I'd actually had some food on the table
huh
so it was an obvious case of realizing
that I didn't know I had yet to learn
how to ask questions if you ask the
questions that just can you give it can
you give a gift yes give all sorts of
gifts so took a while to realize that I
needed to be as philosophical rigorous
when it came to the questions I asked
people as I was when I was
philosophizing with them so the question
how much are you able to give to me some
material needs is a question I have
vetted each and each part of that
question which would be another two of
these stoechas would take a while to
unpack and then the question itself
allowed there to be a specific clear
answer yeah what's what's coming up for
me right there is because right now what
to gifticon imagine have this like a
blurb on the website which you help
massage a little bit and like I like the
idea of just sort of nudges the wrong
word but just sort of direct people
about what gifts are most would be most
alive for you because right now we have
money would be good but it's not maybe
the main one like right now is sort of
help you know like like just like maybe
help like marketing events or organizing
stuff on the website but I haven't
really got much thought or figured out
how to kind of ask for that and what's
coming up right now since we're running
out of time maybe you mean calling other
people who become Stewart's like this
you know we can have like a jam session
to kind of figure that out yeah that's
really great since we're running out of
time I'll just say that I learned as I
was telling Raya that the question has
to be very clear and that can be a broad
question it's just a very clear broad
question but if you just amazed you know
on the stove if you just say this exists
in a gift economy and you feel called to
give
please do you're not giving me it's a
little bit like going to this retreat
and they say please give Donna I don't
know what I have no III can't think with
that I can't think it through you're not
giving me anything I like to tell people
that it's a little bit like you're not
giving me a tire on the ground I can't
get any purchase so philosophy needs the
tire in the ground to get purchase
mm-hmm yeah like that so um let's close
this up here do you have any before I
make closing announcements you have any
closing thoughts yourself Andrew I hope
this was helpful it's it's a little bit
hard to condense a decade into 55
minutes or so yeah everything that
everything was asked about today I have
some way or another thought about
everything I wasn't asked today I may
have thought about mistakes I've made
have shown up iteratively throughout the
course of conversations well that's
where it's a little bit like this fine
tuning over and over again until it
becomes the crystalline clear and when
that so then I get a chance to hum along
with people and it's so wonderful just
to see people picking up the tune yes
it's so simple for them they get it it's
kind of cool that you're not alone in
this conversation anymore because you
know I'm here Colin's here and so we can
start like you know singing together and
figuring it out and how the gift economy
looks and different sort of mediums or
whatnot
sure yeah I just want to say that I'm
gonna be I've been doing more of these
conversations perhaps to this elsewhere
too so please listen to a podcast I'll
be having with Colin on Zion 2.0 podcast
enough plugging plugging kind of guy
push I'm saying if you want to learn
more and I'll probably be talking with
partisan Toronto fairly soon and then I
also know that the one person I believe
here is writing a book about me and a
gift economy so
that might be helpful one once it's out
very cool so I'll make some closing
thoughts in a moment but Angela thanks
so much for coming today my friend it
was greatly appreciated there's a bunch
of events you know just check the
website there was a few facilitators in
the room since today was a kind of light
mood I'm glad that people got to see the
lighter side of you and you and myself
you know I think we have a proclivity
with when we work together like have
cartoonish seriousness sometimes you
know and so I think it's it's good this
is it the Japanese out but I was worried
yeah yeah and the pirate the pirate suit
I was wearing so Rhea you've got an
event coming up and maybe you can just
tell us about it so speaking I'm like
lighter sides Sunday night is kind of
like a community night I think we landed
on the name oxytocin party and the
reason I feel passionate about oxytocin
is because it's the chemical foundation
for trusting others and it helps us work
together for a common purpose and I
really believe that here at the stove
were like building kind of like a family
and it might not be exactly clear what
we're working towards but I know that
we're working towards something and so
sunday is really just putting us maybe
in a different state I would call it
more of like a play shop and to just
have a lot of fun with each other and
connect and maybe new silly ways and
yeah develop just like a deeper trust
with one another and yeah see each other
in fonder ways so you guys are
interested you come and hang out and
Rio's telling me some of the exercises
she had in mind I'm like nervous already
so that means I'm at my edge come by
major of development right now so yeah
again the stola is operating on a gift
economy and I have to get a better spiel
at the end and now that uh I just heard
hinges talk so this send this website
and then you can look at it and then
let me know how I could maybe present
yeah if you if you if you feel if you
feel a sense of abundance after this
conversation sometime you have more than
enough for yourself and your family you
feel a sense of abundance more than more
than enough to go around and if there is
something welling up in you maybe you
can put it into words or maybe you can
pin the words think about that welling
up we've had that experience then all
you would do is
put it in a form and you would you had
directed a Peter in his life or directly
that the stoah acted the stomach and
hopefully you would include it no I
think it's a very important to include a
note mmm along with them they'd say
thank you very much no I want to support
where you're killing I want to support
this whole place of practice I want it
to continue beautiful alright well thank
you my friend thank you everyone for
coming up today that's fun
take care everyone